Guide to the South Africa documentary photographs collection, 1940s-circa 2013, bulk 1960s-2013 RL.01129
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Beyond the Barricades: Popular Resistance in South Africa, 1981-1988, 79 prints
  - Omar Badsha, 1981-1987, 16 prints (Box 1)
    Specific subjects include South African political organizations and individuals such as the African National Congress (ANC) Women's League, the United Democratic Front (UDF), Inkatha Freedom Party, Natal Indian Congress, Ismail Meer, Dorothy Nyembe, Archie Gumede, Billy Nair, and Chief Buthelezi. They document protests, strikes, police confronting activists, mourners at funerals, and other events under apartheid.
    Other images by Badsha can be found in the Cordoned Heart series.
  - Julian Cobbing, 1986, 2 prints (Box 1)
    Photographs document funeral protests by the African National Congress and the East Cape United Democratic Front.
  - Gille de Vlieg, 1984-1986, 5 prints (Box 1)
    Photographs document a FEDTRAW protest, police violence, a woman holding a bloody sheet, an injured protester, and a speech by Archbishop Desmond Tutu.
  - Paul Grendon, 1985, 1 print (Box 1)
    Portrait of body of 11-year old Michael Cheslyn Miranda in a coffin at his funeral.
  - Dave Hartman, 1985-1986, 4 prints (Box 1)
    Photographs depict protests, and UNC and UDF funerals.
  - Steve Hilton-Barber, 1986-1987, 2 prints (Box 1)
    Photographs depict a woman overcome by tear gas at a funeral protest, and a speaker and coffins at a funeral.
  - Rashid Lombard, 1985, 1 print (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts arrests at a United Women's Organization (UWO) protest.
  - Roger Meintjies, 1987, 2 prints (Box 1)
    Photographs depict ANC and UDF protests.
  - Gideon Mendel, 1985-1987, 13 prints (Box 1)
    There are images of UDF protests, funerals and protests at funerals, a mother saying goodbye to her activist son, the 101 Battalion of the South Africa Defense Force in Capetown, police beating protesters, and the arrest of a UDF leader.
  - Eric Miller, 1986-1987, 3 prints (Box 1)
    Images are of National Union of Mine Workers (NUMW) and COSATU protests. Other images by Miller can be found in the Then and Now series.
  - Santu Mofokeng, 1987, 1 print (Box 1)
    Photograph depicts women mourning for the death of an ANC member.
  - Themba Nkosi, 1985, 1 print (Box 1)
    Image is of a police special forces squad in the Transvaal, standing next to the body of a dead person. These units became widely known as "death squads."
  - Cedric Nunn, 1986-1988, 2 prints (Box 2)
    One image is of Chief Buthelezi and Goodwill Zwelithini, leaders of the Kwazulu homeland and the government-supported Inkatha movement. The second image is of a mother mourning the loss of two sons killed in Inkatha violence. Other images by Nunn can be found in the Cordoned Heart, Then and Now, and Underexposed series.
  - Billy Paddock, 1986-1987, 3 prints (Box 2)
    Photographs document a funeral, houses burned in Durban during Pondo/Zulu clashes, and a man murdered in Pondo/Zulu violence.
  - Myron Peters, 1984, 1 print (Box 2)
    Photograph is of participants at the Natal Indian Congress.
  - Chris Qwazi, 1986, 1 print (Box 2)
    Photograph is of police and mourners at a funeral.
  - Jeeva Rajgopaul, 1986, 1 print (Box 2)
    Image is of striking workers in Durban putting on a play. Another print by Rajgopaul is found in the Cordoned Heart series.
  - Guy Tillim, 1986, 3 prints (Box 2)
    Photographs represent a funeral, a rally, and homes burning during "white-headband" vigilante violence near Cape Town. Other images by Tillim can be found in the Cordoned Heart and Then and Now series.
  - Zubeida Vallie, 1985, 1 print (Box 2)
    Photograph is of young South African pallbearers at a funeral.
  - Paul Weinberg, 1980-1987, 16 prints (Box 2)
    Photographs document spectators at the Delmas trial; members of the Black Sash Society marching; UDF (United Democratic Front) and ANC (African National Congress) events, including a UDF concert celebrating the Freedom Charter; police confronting protesters; Leandra Youth Congress members on a road; a policeman informing a family of an execution; and scenes of labor meetings and protests. Notable individuals include labor activist Albertina Sisulu, P.W. Botha at a military parade in Pretoria, and Mrs. Botha and Mrs. Tshabalala, wife of the mayor of Soweto, at a ceremony in Soweto. Some of the images were not used in the book, Beyond the Barricades.
    Other images by Weinberg can be found in the Cordoned Heart and Then and Now series.
- The Cordoned Heart, 1979-1984, 184 prints
  These black-and-white images came out of a documentary project by the photographic collective Afrapix, as part of the Second Carnegie Inquiry into Poverty and Development in South Africa. They document a crucial period of protest and social upheaval in South African history, and focus on poverty and the daily lives of people living under apartheid. Photographs depict neighborhoods, rural and urban residences, social life, families, work conditions, events in South African history such as forced relocations, and scenes of political or labor conflict.
  Twenty photographers are represented, with their work arranged in this order: Paul Alberts, Joseph Alphers, Omar Badsha, Michael Barry, Bee Berman, Michael Davies, David Goldblatt, Paul Konings, Lesley Lawson, Chris Ledechowski, Rashid Lombard, Ben Maclennan, Jimi Matthews, Gideon Mendel, Cedric Nunn, Myron Peters, Berney Perez, Jeeva Rajgopaul, Wendy Schwegmann, and Paul Weinberg. The matted and unmatted gelatin silver prints range in size from approximately 12x16 to 16x20 inches, with duplicates of images found across size groups.
  Textual materials include exhibit brochures and an exhibit installation guide. There is also a limited edition portfolio with ten signed photographs selected from the exhibit; prints have been housed with their respective photographers. Many of the photographs are also available as digital images mounted on the library server; please contact Research Services for access.
  The prints in this series were part of the Cordoned Heart exhibit, curated by Cornell Capa, Alex Harris, and Margaret Sartor, which appeared originally at the International Center of Photography in 1986 and toured for a number of years afterwards. An accompanying book, South Africa: The Cordoned Heart (1986), was edited in part by Afrapix member Omar Badsha. There are some images used in the book which are not present in this collection. In addition, there are several unidentified prints which do not appear in the book.
  - Paul Alberts, 1979-circa 1983, 21 prints
    Images were taken in the homeland of Bophuthatswana, the Crossroads camp, and Kew Town, with settings and subjects such as public housing for "colored," apartment interiors, family groups, unemployed men, children playing outside, and women cooking.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 12 prints (Box 2)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 6 prints (Box 5)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 6)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 13)
  - Joseph Alphers, 1983, 10 prints
    Images were taken in Lesotho, and document the effects of South Africa's migrant work culture. Subjects include mine workers, unemployed men, families waiting for remittance pay, as well as a soccer game, a child herding cattle, an elderly woman, and other scenes in rural areas.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 6 prints (Box 2)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 11)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 13)
  - Omar Badsha, 1981-1983, 31 prints
    Images document the daily life of unemployed men, pensioners, and people living in compounds and shantytowns in rural areas. Other scenes include trade union meetings and strikes. Settings include a funeral, street scenes, meetings of residents and their attorneys, religous events, removal protests and a march. Some images were shot in urban and rural Lesotho, others in the rural Transkei, Kwazulu, and the Inanda shantytown.
    Persons of note in the photos of opposition movements are Albertina Sisulu, Dr. Essop Jassat, Nokukhanya Luthuli, and Paul David (Natal Indian Congress). Other images by Badsha can be found in the Beyond the Barricades series.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 11 prints (Box 2)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 4 prints (Box 6)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 4 prints (Box 7)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 11)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 3 prints (Box 13)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 14)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Michael Barry, 1980-1981, 6 prints
    Portraits and scenes from Haven Night Shelter in Capetown, South Africa, make up this grouping of images by Barry.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 7)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Bee Berman, 1983-1984, 5 prints
    Series was shot in the town of George and surrounding rural districts, between Capetown and Port Elizabeth, and portrays the life of impoverished residents. Subjects include an Anglican church congregation, a disabled farm laborer, and scenes from the city center, a municipal compound, and a village.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 3 prints - 2 unique images (Box 3)
      Scope and Contents
      There are two copies of one print.
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Michael Davies, 1983-1984, 5 prints
    Images form part of a photo series entitled "Segregated Weekend," created with Joseph Alphers (images by Alphers are housed separately). Photos by Davies are of black children at an amusement park in Strandfontein, adults of color at the beach in Silwerstroomstrand and around an open-air gambling table in Guguletu, and a black soccer crowd in Durban.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 4 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 8)
  - David Goldblatt, circa 1985, 14 prints
    These images capture the grueling nighttime travels of black commuters who ride buses from a large resettlement reserve called KwaNdebele to Pretoria in order to work. One print has two copies. Other images by Goldblatt can be found in the Then and Now series.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 7 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints (Box 8)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 11)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Paul Konings, 1980, 4 prints
    Konings' portraits are of a man in a migrant labor camp called Gordon's Bay, and a man and two male children at a migrant labor camp, Langa, near Capetown.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 8)
  - Lesley Lawson, 1982, 7 prints
    This body of work focuses on service workers, and poverty in Soweto and in resettlement camps. Images include portraits of women housekeepers and cleaners at work and at home, squatters and other people living in camps, and interiors of dwellings.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 8)
  - Chris Ledechowski, 1982-1983, 10 prints
    Images were taken at the homeland of Venda in the Transvaal Province, and at the Crossroads squatter camp near Capetown. Scenes include plastic shelters, a woman dismantling a temporary shelter before police raids, and portraits of the family members of a cattle owner.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 7 prints - 6 unique images (Box 3)
      One print of nighttime in a camp has two copies.
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 3 prints (Box 8)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 1 print (Box 11)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Rashid Lombard, 1983, 2 prints
    Image is of students confronting a candidate for Parliament in Cape Town; printed in two sizes.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 8)
  - Ben Maclennan, 1980-1982, 16 prints
    Photographs come from two series that document single-sex men's compounds (created along with photographer Paul Alberts, whose images are in a separate folder), and life in the resettlement camps in the Ciskei homeland. Images document the process by which families are moved by the government from one camp to another, and daily life for the gold miners in the single-sex hostels.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 7 prints (Box 9)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 11)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 14)
  - Jimi Matthews, 1983
    Photograph of a migrant sheep shearer at work in Moorreesburg, from a series called Sheep shearers of the Karoo.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 3)
  - Gideon Mendel, 1984, 6 prints
    Series consists of portraits of squatters - men, women, and children - living in Hout Bay, a fishing community near Cape Town.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 4 prints (Box 3)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 9)
  - Cedric Nunn, 1983, 4 prints
    Nunn's photographs document the effects of the government's decentralization labor policies, portraying men and women commuters walking along a road at an industrial park in Isithebe, north of Durban, and an open-air barber working in the same industrial zone. Other images by Nunn can be found in the Beyond the Barricades, Then and Now, and Underexposed series.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 3 prints - 2 unique images (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 9)
  - Berney Perez, 1983, 4 prints
    Images were taken at a railway town where there is high unemployment and poverty. Scenes are of a family indoors, people dancing and gathering in the street, and a woman who lives under a bridge.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 4 prints - 3 unique images (Box 4)
  - Myron Peters, 1984
    One image of female entrepreneurs - carpet sellers - in Umbumbulu, Kwazulu. Another print by Peters is found in the Beyond the Barricades series.
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 9)
  - Jeeva Rajgopaul, 1983
    Image shows a farm laborer. Another image by Rajgopaul is found in the Beyond the Barricades series.
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 9)
  - Wendy Schwegmann, 1983-1984, 9 prints
    Images in one group document men, women, and children living in Alexandra township, near Johannesburg. Another series documents forced removals in Magopa and Rooigrond, and includes images of a vigil with Archbishop Desmond Tutu, a classroom, a pensioner in his garden, and people in the process of being moved from their homes.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 3 prints (Box 4)
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints (Box 10)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 11)
  - Paul Weinberg, 1984 and undated, 22 prints
    Images taken by Weinberg derive from three series: farmworkers and child labor in the Transvaal; farmers' association meetings and farm workers in Reserve Four (Kwazulu); and labor strikes in Pretoria, Johannesburg, and Durban. Other documentary images by Weinberg can be found in the Beyond the Barricades and Then and Now series.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 8 prints (Box 4)
      One of the eight prints is unattributed to Weinberg but appeared in the series with his other prints; it is of a female child farm laborer. It does not appear in the book.
    - Matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 6 prints (Box 10)
    - Cordoned Heart portfolio: matted 12x16 inch gelatin silver print, 1 print (Box 11)
    - 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints - 3 unique images (Box 12)
    - Matted 16x20 inch gelatin silver prints, 2 prints (Box 14)
  - Unidentified photographers, undated
    These prints by unidentified photographers depict black farmworkers, children at a UDF rally, an elderly black woman voter at the polls, and a long shot of traditional stone huts on an arid hillside.
    - 12x16 inch gelatin silver prints, 5 prints - 4 unique images (Box 4)
      These prints appeared with the Cordoned Heart series but are unattributed, and do not appear in the book. There are two copies of one print.
  - The Cordoned Heart exhibit materials, 1986-1991 and undated
    - Exhibit installation guide and brochures, 1986-1991 (Box 15)
    - Exhibit print captions, partial list, circa 1998 (Box 15)
    - Photocopies of Cordoned Heart Portfolio introduction pages, circa 1986 (Box 15)
      Photocopied pages from the Cordoned Heart portfolio, published in conjunction with the book by the same name, 1986. They consist of an introduction to the portfolio, a forward by Bishop Desmond Tutu, a poem which appeared in the book, and a list of the seven photographers and information on the prints. The original sheets are found in this collection in the portfolio box along with the original prints.
- Then and Now: Eight South African Photographers, 1963-2006, 160 prints
  The Cordoned Heart series features the work of eight South African photographers documenting South Africa before and after apartheid: David Goldblatt, George Hallett, Eric Miller, Cedric Nunn, Guy Tillim, Paul Weinberg, Graeme Williams, and Gisèle Wulfsohn. The 160 color and black-and-white prints were shown together in a 2008 exhibit at Duke University, curated by South African photographer Paul Weinberg, and later published in book form.
  The photographers were asked to contribute twenty of their most significant images: ten taken during South African apartheid, and ten taken in the years following democratic elections in 1994. The apartheid-era images portray the segregated and impoverished lives, street violence, protests, and funerals that marked these decades; and the rapidly changing social life, new relationships, continued political struggle, the AIDS crisis, and the after-effects of civil war that characterized the post-apartheid period.
  The photographs in the two series "Then" and "Now" are a mix of black-and-white gelatin silver prints and color inkjet or chromotype prints, with many of the black-and-white prints coming from the earlier period and color from later decades. They all measure approximately 12x17 inches, and are housed in 16x20 inch hinged mats. Each photographer's 20-print set is divided into the two subgroups "Then" and "Now."
  All of the images are available online as a Duke Libraries digital exhibit. The series also contains a digitized audio file of speakers and musicians recorded at the exhibition's opening, also available through the online exhibit. The speakers and musicians are: Kay-Robert Volkwijn, Karin Shapiro, Karen Jean Hunt, and Roger Lucey.
  - David Goldblatt, Then / Now, 1963-2006, 15 prints (Box 16)
    Goldblatt's images show National Party commandos, portraits of South Africans, street scenes in Johannesburg, landscapes, and life for whites and blacks in apartheid and post-apartheid in rural and urban South Africa. One portrait is of Margaret Mcingana from Soweto, who as a singer became known as Margaret Singana. Other images by Goldblatt can be found in the Cordoned Heart series.
  - David Goldblatt, Now, 1963-2006, 5 prints (Box 17)
  - George Hallett, Then / Now, 1968-2005, 9 prints (Box 17)
    Includes photographs of scenes from urban life during and after apartheid. Subjects include Cape Town's District Six before efforts to demolish it, two women meeting Nelson Mandela on his release from prison, and depictions of religious rituals in Johannesburg and Cape Town from 1994 to 2004. Among the portraits are many of exiled South African activists and writers, as well as intellectuals and activists living in South Africa after the fall of apartheid.
  - George Hallett, Then / Now, 1968-2005, 11 prints (Box 18)
  - Eric Miller, Then / Now, 1984-2006, 14 prints (Box 19)
    Images from the apartheid era document protests, arrests, riot police and military operations, and South Africa's first democratic elections in 1994. Color images from after the fall of apartheid include Muslims celebrating the end of Ramadan, a women's soccer team, a Cape Town beach, and an LGBT street party in Cape Town. Other images are of an aid center and other scenes in South Sudan and a mental hospital in Sierra Leone.
    Other images by Miller can be found in the Beyond the Barricades and Cordoned Heart series.
  - Eric Miller, Now, 1984-2006, 6 prints (Box 20)
  - Cedric Nunn, Then, 1982-2005, 9 prints (Box 20)
    Images of life under apartheid are mainly from Kwazulu Natal, and include laborers and farmers, families, a funeral for youths killed in violence, a grieving mother, and a wedding party. Post-apartheid images are of street scenes in poor areas of Johannesburg, color portraits of South Africans, and a wedding party in Kwazulu Natal. There are also a few color images taken in Angola.
    Other images by Nunn can be found in the Beyond the Barricades and Underexposed series.
  - Cedric Nunn, Then / Now, 1982-2005, 11 prints (Box 21)
  - Guy Tillim, Then, 1986-2006, 7 prints (Box 22)
    Black-and-white photographs from the decades under apartheid depict rival groups fighting for control of a settlement in Cape Town in 1986, and life for rural people in Transkei. The color images taken post-apartheid include election rally scenes in Kinshasa with Congolese opposition leader Bemba, and several scenes from daily life in the Hillbrow apartment towers of Johannesburg and the suburb of Berea, Durban.
    Other images by Tillim can be found in the Beyond the Barricades series.
  - Guy Tillim, Then / Now, 1986-2006, 13 prints (Box 23)
  - Paul Weinberg, Then, 1979-2005, 7 prints (Box 24)
    Images taken during apartheid document life in 1980s poor areas of Johannesburg and rural locations, protesters and tanks, forced removals in Magopa, and a bushman in Namibia. Post-apartheid images are of ritual dances in Kwazulu Natal, political campaigning, rallies, repatriations following forced removals, and scenes related to the end of apartheid and a loosening of restrictions. With the exception of one print from "Now," all are black-and white images.
    Other work by Paul Weinberg can be found in the Beyond the Barricades and Cordoned Heart series.
  - Paul Weinberg, Then / Now, 1979-2005, 13 prints (Box 25)
  - Graeme Williams, Then, 1987-2006, 6 prints (Box 26)